Guide to the Theodore John Kreps Papers
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
Theodore John Kreps Papers
1926-1962
SC0207
Kreps, Theodore J. (Theodore John ), b. 1897
14 Linear feet (20 boxes)
Reports, memos, surveys, statistics, legal documents, and some printed material. Arrangement is chronological. Subjects included are cartels, anti-trust, labor, conservation, investment, reciprocal trade, government purchasing, production, government regulations, inflation, land-lease, war mobilization, and international trade.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Biography
Theodore John Kreps, born 13 January 1897 in Prinsburg, Minnesota, received his Ph.D from Harvard in 1928. He was professor of business economics at Stanford (1930-1962; emeritus, 1962- ).
1897, January 13 Born, Prinsburg, Minnesota
1917-1919 1st Lt..A.B.F.
1919 Married Esther E1vira Cersberg (six children)
1920 A.B., University of Cclorado
1920-1923 Instructor of history and economics at Colorado State °rep. - Boulder
19214 A.N., Harvard
1925-1930 Instructor of economics and tutor history, government and eccnomics at Harvard
1926 Frederick Sheldon Fellow
1928 Ph.D., Harvard
1928-1929 Laura Spelman Rockefeller Fellow, Bureau of International Research
1930 At Stanford since 1930
l935 Chief, Statistics Section, National Recovery Administration; Chairman, Co-ordinating Committee of Central Statistical Board and Works Progress Administration
1936 December Representative U.S. Government to Preparatory Technical Tripartite Conference on Reduction of Hours in Chemical Industry, Geneva, Switzerland
1937, Summer Economic Adviser U.S. Maritime Commission 1938, 1941-1945 Economic Adviser, Anti-trust Division, Department of Justice
1939-1940 Economic Adviser, Temporary National Economic Commission
1914, Summer Chief Consultant, Office of Price Administration
1942-1941 Chief Economic Adviser, Board of Economic Warfare
1949-1951 Staff Director of the Joint Committee on the Economic Report
1951 Ford Foundation exchange Professor to the Free University of Ber1in, Author of books, articles and reviews
Description of the Collection
Reports, memos, surveys, statistics, legal documents, and some printed material. Arrangement is chronological. Subjects included are cartels, anti-trust, labor, conservation, investment, reciprocal trade, government purchasing, production, government regulations, inflation, land-lease, war mobilization, and international trade.
Access Terms
Kreps, Theodore J. (Theodore John ), b. 1897; Managerial economics.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Cartel speeches; Webb-Pomerene Act; League of Nations publications (International Labour Office & Economic & Financial Section - standard of living of workers, dumping, monopolies); Federal Trade Commission anti-trust hearing; Income.
  - 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Price fixing; Cartels - German; Electrical industry trade practice rules; National Unemployment Program of the People's Lobby; Conservation (lumber); Dye Cartel; Investment.
  - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Social audit; Anti-trust; Wholesale Drug Industry trade practice rules; Labor; Corporations.
  - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Reciprocal trade - chemical; Government purchasing; profits, losses & business assets; German tobacco industry; Labor; Hugh B. White memo on corrosion resisting steel; Fire extinguishers; anti-trust; A.F. of L. Monthly Survey of Business; 1926 Price level; Exchange of corresnondence with Dept. of State re: entry of foreign ships into U.S. ports (copies); Investment; Production & Price Control in Bituminous Coal Mining.
  - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The Consumer, Statistics on Copper, 1926 Price level; Labor; Resale Price (Goodyear case); Government stimuli (silver policy); Formal complaints of Federal Trade Commission for unfair competition and price discrimination (anti-trust); answer to complaint; hearing; National Consumer News Proposed Revision of Anti-trust Laws; Foreign Systems Communist Election Platform; Consumer Credit, Debt & taxes.
  - 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Anti-trust; 1926 Price level; Depreciation reserve policies; Industrial mobilization Plan; Housing; Resale price maintenance; unfair competition; Consumers' Research Bulletin; Labor; Primary producers; International organization of Big Business; Burial vaults; Tax; American Merchant Marine; Government aid; Technical Progress & Agricultural Depression; Food & Drugs Act; Installment selling; Price & production control in British industry; Conservation; Agriculture; Bus, reserves & economic stability.
  - 1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1938 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Price competition; Price discrimination; Fence Consumers'Research Bulletin; Conservation; Income Tax; Silver; Summaries of Federal Trade Commission cases, etc.; Recession; 1926 Price level; Statistical Handbook on Federal Finances; Problem of Big Business; Patents investigation; Canadian Tobacco Distribution Combine; Government Aid; Housing -paint & varnish; Caltar Dyes; Re-sale Price Maintenance; Raw materials; Tariff Removal; Trade Barriers; Consumer Protection; Electrical - anti-trust case; small business
  - 1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Price competition; Price discrimination; Fence ConSumers'Research Bulletin; Conservation; Income Tax; Silver; Summaries of Federal Trade Commission cases, etc.; Recession; 1926 Price level; Statistical Handbook on Federal Finances; Problem of Big Business; Patents investigation; Canadian Tobacco Distribution Combine; Government Aid; Housing -paint & varnish; Caltar Dyes; Re-sale Price Maintenance; Raw materials; Tariff Removal; Trade Barriers; Consumer Protection; Electrical - anti-trust case; small business
  - 1939 March-April (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Trade barriers; American rural refugees; Primary producers; Government investment; Consumer protection; Investment problem; Labor
  - l939 May-July (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Potash; Unfair competition (Robinson-Patman); Consumer protection; Tariff removal; International Cartels (I.G. Farben, etc.); Federal Surplus Commodities Corporation; Prices; Electric Home and Farm Authority Investment; Interstate trade barriers; Industries
  - 1939 August (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Government subsidies (Monopoly Control Bill); Ownership; Government regulation.
  - 1939 September (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Anti-trust indictments and complaints (unfair competition, cartels, etc.).
  - 1939 October-December (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Labor; Anti-trust complaints; Consumer protection; Government Information Handbook (?); Planned society; Business Publicity; Government subsidies (and TLS 1940 of George C. Gaede); Government regulation (of competition); Govenment regulation (of competition); labor; Labor costs; National Association of Manufacturers; l926 Price level; Price stabilization (British Program for Armament Plant Expansion, 1935, 1939); Resale.
  - 1940 January-April (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Manufacture (NLR Act) Labor (T.L.S. of M.H. Hedges, Director of Research, International Brotherhood of Electrical workers); Anti-trust findings, orders indictment, complaint; Trade Practice conf. agreements; Anti-trust Laws; Fire equipment; American shipping needs; Small Business (Robinson-Patma); Technology; Labor.
  - 1940 May-August (Box 4, Folder 18)
    National Business affairs; Recovery program; Anti-trust; agents; Cost of Flotation for Small issues; Capital structure; Telephone service; A.F. of L. Monthly Survey of Business; National Defense; Optical; Fair Trade and Unfair Practices Acts.
  - 1940 September-December (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Anti-trust; Industry's Job Under the Defense Program; National Defense; Basing Point; Brink-of-War Planning Capital Expansion, Employment & Economic Stability-; Government Purchasing; Labor; Trade barriers; "Why France Fell."
  - l941 January-March (Box 5, Folder 20)
    California Government income and expenditures; Anti-trust British Wartime Control of Copper, Lead & Zinc; Consumer Education; Individual annual savings and underspending; "Amortization Deduction;" T.L.S. re: Fair Trade and Unfair Practices Act; Labor.
  - 1941 April-November (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Voluntary standards; Anti-trust & Defense Program and Price indexes; Governmental Defense Program; Governmental marketing barriers; Anti-trust violation; Dept. of Justice, minutes of and memos to Policy Board of Anti-trust Division (Temporary National Economic Division); National Defense, Industry and Profiteering (group of letters and papers going back to 1939, includes T.L.S W.J. Buttfield, Arthur B. Gardner); American Merchant Marine; Economic Defense Board; Food Service Equipment; Pipe Line Costs Tariffs; Calif. Fields; National Resources Commission; Consumer Education; Labor; Argentine tungsten; China tungsten (back to 1940).
  - 1941 December and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Britain - inflation; Palmer Harmon shipping situation (from July), Merchant Marine, etc. (A.H.S. Palmer Harmon to Mr. Farley); Fats & oils; Deficit Spending and the Defense Effort 1931 - 19141" (paper for Business 390 in Autumn l941 by Lawrence V. Metcalf and C. Howard Janin); Anti-trust; German-Argentina; Compulsory licensing; German Military Administration in Occupied France (diagram); The Soviet Power; Price Ceiling Regulations; Canadian Industries, Ltd.; Trade Barriers
  - 1941 December and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - 1942 January-April (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Inflation; Price Supply Controls - chemical industry; Nationa.l Defense; League of Nations Association Iron and Steel Scrap (memo by W.S. Whitehead); CAA Medical Exams; Patents; Labor; Cotton - Haiti; Reoccupied areas; antimony; Corning Glass and G.E. - lamp case; Lend lease - Board of Economic Warfare; Cotton - Peru; Price ceiling; Rubber - Peru; Metals Mexico; anti-trust and Advertising; Mobilization of Resources; Importation from Soviet Union.
  - 1942 May-June (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Rubber- Costa Rica, Nicaragua; Rotenone - Peru; Fats and oils; Indian shellac; Flax - Peru; Quebracho; Henequen - Mexico; Australian Economic Control; Strategic materials - Latin America; Reconstruction; British relations; Price Control; Raw materials; Rubber survey; Quinine - Costa Rica Petroleum industry; Anti-trust; Warsaw Ghetto economic condition - German financing.
  - 1942 May-June (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - 1942 July (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Axis activities - Latin America; BEW operations Anti-Malarials procurement; Canadian nickel; Industrial diamonds; Economic intelligence; Preclusive buying; Alcohol sales; Rubber, tungsten, tin -Bolivia; Cotton - Nicaragua; Balsa wood - Ecuador; Australia - specified articles production capacity (clothing, troops); Labor and Population Intelligence (International); Quinine; Rubber - Ecuador; Quebracho (TLS of James S. Martin) - anti-trust; public utility taxation; Rubber - Honduras.
  - 1942 August (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Export and Trade Control - Latin America; Rubber - Trinidad and Tobago, Br. Honduras, Br. Guiana; Ixtl Mexico; Netherlands Indies Intelligence; Abaca -Costa Rica; - Imports; Rubber - El Salvador; Peru - economic and political Raw materials regulation; Chile -prices of metals, etc.; Postwar - Pacific relations.
  - 1942 September-October (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Rubber - Guatemala; Mahogany - Guatemala; Rubber - Mexico; Rubber survey; BEW operations; Sisal - Mexico; Abaca - Guatemala, Honduras; Rubber - Panama; United Nations Raw Materials administration; U.S. Aviation Corp. - French subsidiary; Canadian metals; German trademarks; coffee, Agave - Haiti; Joint Preemption; Money exchange - Chile; Metals -Minerals Division Progress Report; Brazil - publicty for rubber program, etc.; Flax - Canada; Labor clauses - BEW; Inflation - Bolivia; Labor reserve - Mexico; South African War Program - aid; Rubber - Venezuela; Chile - economic conditions; Critical materials; Fibers; Inflation - Cnile; Brazil - economic conditions; Labor clauses - Metals Reserve Co. - Bolivia and Montezuma Copper Co., Mexico
  - 1942 November (Box 6, Folder 30)
    Cocoa - Brazil; Inflation - Bolivia; Cartels; Raw materials; Bismutin; Antitrust; Carburators, Cinchona - Peru; Copper, etc. - Chile, l942-43 (TLS in Sp. Jose Macias Contreras); Labor; Business activities of Amer. organizations in ememy occupied countries; Banque de Paris; Mercury; Imports; Mani fiber - Sisal; Wool - Uruguay; Sisal - Bahama; Labor - Bolivia, etc.; Defense; Dyestuffs; Rubber; Transportation - Indo-China, Thailand, etc. - Japanese activities
  - 1942 December and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 31)
    Importation - strategic materials - air; Contra committments and deliveries- foreign metals and minerals; Anti-trust; Cartels; Banque de Paris; Social insurance; Subsidies - Caribbean; Intelligence Report - British Ministry of Economic Warfare -German -Europe Far East; Inflation and profiteering Mexico; Flotation of joint Angle-American loans in Latin America; War Economics and Armament Office of German High Command; Webb-Pomerene; Quinine; Commodity agreements; Bolivian labor; Labor - Brazil; Bolivia (to 1944); Labor - Ecuador; Economic warfare; electricaL; Fats oils; Inflation; Labor -Rubber; Mexican Mercury; -efina; Methane Steam Ammonia Plants to Russia; chemical industry - Mexico; British chart - administrative war Cabinet
  - 1942 December and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Importation - strategic materials - air; Contra committments and deliveries- foreign metals and minerals; Anti-trust; Cartels; Banque de Paris; Social insurance; Subsidies - Caribbean; Intelligence Report - British Ministry of Economic Warfare -German -Europe Far East; Inflation and profiteering Mexico; Flotation of joint Angle-American loans in Latin America; War Economics and Armament Office of German High Command; Webb-Pomerene; Quinine; Commodity agreements; Bolivian labor; Lsabor - Brazil; Bolivia (to 1944) Labor - Ecuador; Economic warfare. electricaL; Fats oils; Inflation; Labor -Rubber; Mexican Mercury; -efina; Methane Steam Ammonia Plants to Russia; chemical industry - Mexico; British chart - administrative war Cabinet
  - l943 January (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Fats and oils; Siemens and Halske, A.G.; Bolivia - labor; Kuhlmann; Inflation - Chile; Peru - economic developments; BEW program; British blockade; German - industrial offensive; Italy - food situation; Quinine; BEW Organizational Handbook.
  - 1943 February (Box 6, Folder 34)
    Bolivian Labor; Mexico - economic and financial; American business activities in Asian countries; Inflation -Venezuela; Inter-nation economic issues; Food in Russia; Mexican labor; Rubber; Lend-Lease; North African Phosphate cartel; Mexican chick pea; Colombia rubber; Latin America - Axis alien property disposal; Bolivia - mining and raw materials; Fascist economic bankruptcy - Italy; BEW - Departmemt of State; Taxes; Mica.
  - 1943 March (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Commodity Credit Corp. - Mexico; BEW and Commerce Department; Reoccupied - food - Italy; Bolivia; BEW - Office of Imports; Essential industries - soda; strategic materials - Colombia - platinun, cinchon rubber; CivilIan money income; Peru; Mexico - mini Mexican development; Japan's war economy.
  - 1943 April (Box 7, Folder 36)
    Reoccupied areas; Coffee imports: Brazilian labor clauses; FEA purchase arrangements; Bolivian Development Corp.; Uruguayan industry and War; Labor conditions, military highway - Guatemala; Bolivian commerce and industries; inflation - western South America; Axis fuel injection; Foreign Subsidy Company -preliminary report (TLS Ralph W. Bettelheim); File Dollar balances -Mexico; International Telephone Telegraph; Cartels - Pirelli (TLS William T. Stone); Bolivia - tin, tungsten, food, labor, etc. American Ship Owners - just compensation; Latin America - aid to U.S. War effort; Export - Great Britain to Peru; Inflation - Chile; U.S. economic warfare; China - commodity stockpile - air transport.
  - 1943 May (Box 7, Folder 37)
    Water carriers - Transportation service; India speculation; Latin iimerica currents; Drugs chemicals; Kuhlmann; Laval's Bank; South African economy - gold; Rubber; Union of South Africa; Defense Supplies Corp. - India; international Tin Cartel; Bolivia - loan from Argentine bankers; Mexican binder twine; Farben - synthetic nitrate; Equador -government stability; Cartels.
  - l943 June (Box 7, Folder 38)
    Procurement and Developnent - Foreign; Chemicals and Drugs; Airplanes; Moscow Dateline and Mother Russia Kuhlmann - chart; Bolivia - tungsten tax; Bosch - fuel injection; Gold - South Africa; Cartels - German; Mexico; Alcohol - Canada; European Dyestuff Cartel - charts; Cartels; subsidies; Balanced distribution; Mercury Cartel
  - 1943 July (Box 7, Folder 39)
    Bolivia; France; Pyrethrum; Commodities available for air transport - chart; French Dyestuff Industry - Kuhlmann; economic warfare revisions; Inflation Chile; Liberian palm oil; Peru - metals mineral agreement; Britain - wool; Mica; BEW weekly report Cuba - contracts; Commodity Agreements Prospectus; tea - purchase procedure; Black List - Philip's subsidiaries; Webb-Pomerene; Quinine - Axis inventory; Mexican chemical properties - Alien Property seizure; Tin - Netherlands Indies; Patents; Ships compensation for.
  - l943 August (Box 7, Folder 40)
    Foreign projects; Nicaraguan rice; Britain - toward post-war monopoly; Reoccupied areas; Subsidies - foodstuffs (T.L.S. A.N. Fischel, Richard Quinilain, Edwin J. Kuh, T.R. Merryweather), fats and oils, misc. commodities, negotiations reports, deliveries of commodities preclusive operations shipment, rubber (textile div.), fibers; Peru -mine labor; industrial diamonds; Imports; Stockpiles; Farben; Bolivia; Colombian replacement negotiations.
  - 1943 September 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    Canadian nickel; Pomeranz affair - Bolivian labor; Cartels - Latin American subcommittee; Merchant shipping - U.S.; Cattle hides - program; Quebrache industry Joint Anglo-American-Canadian Mission on Hides & Leather to Brazil, Argentina and Uruguay; Japan - Naruo aircraft factory and airfield.
  - 1943 September 15-20 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    Strategic and critical materials - Agreements U.S. and foreign countries; White Paper Policy; Frankfurt, Ger. - industry, transportation, power and defense; European Iron and Steel Cartel - activities in South America; Intercoastal shipping.
  - 1943 September 21- n.d. (Box 8, Folder 43)
    Pirelli Co.; Synthetic rubber - Germany; International regulation of primary products; Bolivia; Nitrogen plant - Poland; U.S. Commercial Co. - foreign purchase, development and activities; Loss to Axis of European areas - economic consequences; White Paper Policy; International Investment Agency; Wartime Liquid Accumulations; Lend-lease; Colombian Progress Report; Intercoastal shipping compensation; Industrial diamonds; Commodity agreements; Societee Generale de Belgique and African Metals Corp. Malaysia - commodity posItion -quinine; Dry cargo vessels.
  - 1943 October 5-15 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    Cartels; Multilateral tariff; Diamonds; International Commodity State Trading; white Paper; International cartels; International Commercial Policy Organization; Taxes.
  - 1943 October 16-n.d. (Box 8, Folder 45)
    Mexican labor; Cellophane - Europe; Coffee - commodity control; International Commodity Policy; Control and Procurement Agencies; Pyrethorum, etc. -Brazil; International Cartels; Foreign trade - post-war; Optical glass - anti-trust; Taxes - social security; Fats and oils; Rubber.
  - 1943 November-December (Box 9, Folder 46)
    Nitric acid - France; N.V. Philips Gloeilampenfabrieken; Brazil - mica; Kalle and Co., A.G.; Belgian Congo - Pyrethrum; FEA & State Department; Stockpiles; U.S. Commercial Co.; Commodity agreements; Strategic and Critical Materials; Foreign procurement financing; industrial diamonds.
  - 1943, n.d., (some pen and pencil notea by Kreps ?) (Box 9, Folder 47)
    Cartels, German and other; Economic Reconstruction and Reconversion; Black Mica; Quinine - Ecuador; Anderson-Clayton; Colombia; Shipping - hull; Antitrust - rubber; Civilian Economy; Relation with Europe; Reports on Argentina, Belgian Congo, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, India, 1942-3, Mexico, Peru, South Africa; Development Corporations (Inter-American) -international investment and development - Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Ecuador (TLS Henry A. Wallace), Honduras, Mexico, SHADA. - Haiti
  - 1943, n.d., (some pen and pencil notea by Kreps ?) (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - 1943, n.d., (some pen and pencil notea by Kreps ?) (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - 1944 January 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    Labor standards - foreign procurement; Carburetors - Axis; banque de l'Indochine; Bondix - axis aircraft starters; Surplus property; Volume of money and price level.
  - 1944 January 18-n.d. (Box 10, Folder 51)
    Patents; Bismuts - Anti-trust; Combined Raw Materials Board; Hochschild case; Postwar plans - United Nations; Corporate profits; Magnesite cartel Industrial alcohol.
  - l944 February (Box 10, Folder 52)
    Commercial Policy - postwar agreements; Military Government - Italy; -Development Corporations; Phosphate - cartel monopoly; Foreign procurement development; Industrial diamonds; Postwar Office of Demobiization; industrialists - 1939 Dusseldorf Conference; Rubber.
  - 1944 March (Box 10, Folder 53)
    Cartel Comm. - Industrial diamonds; Trading with the enemy; Osram G.M.B.H., Cartel Kommanditgesellschaft; International Tin Cartel; (Memo to Jim Baker); Cartels; Japanese Trading Companies in U.S.; Phosphate; Profiteering.
  - 1944 April 1-20 (Box 10, Folder 54)
    SAIAC; Banque de l'Indochine; International Commodity Policy; Cartels - Latin America; Cartel Industrial diamonds; Nersk Hydro and I.G. Farben; Potassium; Patents - Ericsson (TLS Leonard Dorn Industrial diamonds; Surplus Property; Postwar economic policy; IT & T.
  - 1944 April 7 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    Universal Oil Products Co. & Japan Gasoline Co.
  - 1944 April 21-n.d. (Box 10, Folder 56)
    Optical glass - Zeiss; Tin; Phosphate industry; Consent decrees, U.S. monetary control - German circumvention; Carbon black; Africa (includes other material - misc., India, Brazil).
  - 1944 May (Box 10, Folder 57)
    Expert Associations and Sherman Act; N.V. Philips; Hochschild; I.G. Farben & post-war; ~Electronic equipment; Banque Francaise et Italienne Pour l'Amerique du Sud; Asbestos - German barter & financial activities in U.S.; Surplus property; Bolivia; Potash; U.S. connections of Axis concerns; Potash (TLS Homer Jornes); Diamonds.
  - 1944 June (Box 10, Folder 58)
    German lamp industry - postwar; Siemen-Reiniger-Werke; A.G. in Latin America; I.G. Farben industrie Dynamit-Aktien-Gesellschaft; Industrial diamonds; International Cartels (TLS Dean Acheson); Samuel Schweier; Swedish banks - manufacturing interests; Iron and steel - Ubbelohde; Executive Com. on Economic Foreign Policy; Patents tin; Business machines, etc. - Germany econczny.
  - 1944 July 12-14 (Box 10, Folder 59)
    Societe General - Belgian Congo; Phosphate - Export violations; Unilever - fats and oils; Cartels German.
  - 1944 July 17-n.d. (Box 11, Folder 60)
    Cartels - British foreign trade policy; Patents Bayer Products; Wood pulp for Sweden; Nestle - General Milk Cartel; Cartels - British, international (South American), cocoa; Dyestuffs; Cartels; Du Pont - anti-trust; N.V. Philips; Chrysler; Cashew nut shell oil; Iron & Steel industry; Enemy Europe organization.
  - 1944 August-September (Box 11, Folder 61)